<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Zombiecalypse the Blog</title><link href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/feeds/Political%20Theory.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/</id><updated>2013-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Delegated Voting and Classical Theorists III</title><link href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-iii.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Zombiecalypse</name></author><id>tag:zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog,2013-01-15:2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-iii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This continues the series on 
&lt;a href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-ii.html"&gt;delegated voting and classical&amp;nbsp;theories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tocqueville&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tocqueville argues against too much democracy of a state, because it fails to protect minorities against the despotism of the majority. Further, it leads to dull leaders, because the sharp ones are put off by being a puppet to the public and short terms lead to preferring short-sighted to long-term&amp;nbsp;solutions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Short-sighted&amp;nbsp;legislates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to regular indirect democracies, this is even more problematic with delegated voting: the &amp;#8220;term&amp;#8221; of elected officials could potentially be arbitrary short for every domain to which the delegation principle extends (which I will assume to be only the&amp;nbsp;legislature). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Ernesto Dal Bó and Martin Rossi show (&lt;a href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w14511"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Term Length and Political Performance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), being held accountable frequently in the form of elections will decrease the performance consistently across several metrics contrary to what models (by Barro and Ferejohn) would imply, as they argue due to time horizon effects - there is less incentive to invest in the long term, if one might never see it, especially since it might harm the popularity in the short&amp;nbsp;term. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains to be seen if this effect reoccurs in a delegates voting system, where there is no fixed term and no election binary, but while these differences are significant and could well turn the effect around, as it is this remains a possible disadvantage of system that is, should it occur, inherent to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Protection of&amp;nbsp;Minorities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tocqueville (and Mills similarly) further argues, that a democracy needs to take additional measures to protect minorities, because the leaders and the public opinion push in the same direction. If one is opposed to that direction, one faces not only legal consequences, but also social disapproval. The reverse is even more true: a norm might quickly ascend to a law in a direct democracy, as seen with the minaret&amp;nbsp;initiative. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem however is not one that is inherent to liquid democracy and more connected to direct democracy in general. The measures against it are well studies, such as a additional barrier in changing the most fundamental laws, the&amp;nbsp;constitution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often enough, the interpretation of these laws of minimal consensus is not as clear as one would hope - one might even argue that the consensus was only found by leaving the interpretation somewhat open. So even if there was some corpus of laws that we accept as fundamental and eternal, then we would still need an instance that provides a binding interpretation. According to Tocqueville, this instance has to be independent from any public&amp;nbsp;influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to defend liquid democracy from a participatory standpoint, but as we have seen, the concept fits very well into the classical theories of Locke and Rousseau.  It also shares the weaknesses as described by Tocqueville which can not be completely&amp;nbsp;dismissed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liquid democracy might therefore well have been the conclusion of the social contact thought experiments if they took modern technology into&amp;nbsp;account.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Delegated Voting and Classical Theorists I</title><link href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Zombiecalypse</name></author><id>tag:zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog,2013-01-13:2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the modern idea of democracy rose to its contemporary positive connotation,
many theorists held that direct democracy was the ideal, but impractical. Locke
said &lt;strong&gt;quote about how indirect democracy is necessary&lt;/strong&gt; and for Rousseau, only
a small community ensures happiness for its members, because he held it
impossible to have immediate contact in a larger context. These constraints do
not apply as much as they did when the theories were first developed -
geographical distance is but a minor inconvenience in the information age. In
reaction to the possibilities that this gives society, delegated voting
(&lt;em&gt;Designing a Democratic System Based on Voluntary Vote-Delegation&lt;/em&gt;,  James
Green-Armytage) as an alternative  to or synthesis of both representative and
direct systems had been proposed. In this essay I will analyse how the novel
idea fits into the framework that were the basis for the first modern
democratic systems in America and France - &lt;strong&gt;Locke&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Rousseau&lt;/strong&gt;. As I firmly believe that one has to
test their theories against the strongest opponents, I will also add &lt;strong&gt;Tocqueville&lt;/strong&gt; to the list of proponents I will compare&amp;nbsp;to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Delegated&amp;nbsp;Voting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before comparing it to classical approaches, I will shortly introduce the
concept of delegated voting. Like other approaches, every citizen has one vote
and as in a direct democratic setting, this vote can be cast on issues of
public interest, not only for candidates. The novel approach is that the vote
can be transferred from one person to another, that is, I can not only cast my
vote directly for an proposal, but also for the opinion of another fellow
voter, so that they not only decide where their own vote goes, but also where
the votes of the people who vote for them go. I might choose that my expertise
is not sufficient of an issue and lay my trust on an expert, thus closing the
gap between direct voting and&amp;nbsp;representation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this goal it has also been proposed that the delegation can be restricted to
a specific field of expertise. This of course leads to a significant power to
those able to define the category of a proposal. Even now, where the influence
is only an informal one, the framing of an proposal can make or break it. If
the minaret initiative had been discussed as an issue of personal freedom or
business interests (how many jobs could be created by building a minaret in
each village), the proposal might well have taken a different turn. Adding to
that that different people decide on the proposal, depending on what aspect is
chosen, one can only imagine how significant this decision would have&amp;nbsp;been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Locke&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Locke&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Two Treatises on Government&lt;/em&gt; he sets up a scenario of an anarchical
society and argues that for granted property rights and justice, such a society
would introduce a social contract and erect a government. He further argues
that this government would be an representative democracy, because the parties
of the social contract could not decide in a collective, that is a direct
democracy is only possible in a small community. The validity of his argument
can be seen in that even in Switzerland, policy decisions are seldom decided by
the people and for most questions of public interest, its directness is only&amp;nbsp;theoretical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be changed with todays technology, a public discourse of the whole
population can take place in the time a law is proposed until the decision is
made. Public media and especially the internet allow a voter to get many
relevant information. A politically interested citizen can be as informed as
politicians about issues of their choosing. Even politicians can hardly know
every nuance of an issue. Often highly technical issues are decided by people,
who only understand them from a second hand perspective. Locke asserts, that a
politician can find a well rounded view on every decision, but that I think
ceased to be the case, if it ever was. To decide for example, if the patent law
needs to be revised, we&amp;#8217;d first need to understand what 
the current laws allow, what causes problems and finally what law could prevent these problems. The first assessment alone would take a person years, or weeks&amp;nbsp;optimistically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Locke based his treatises on a thought experiment resulting in a social contract, I propose to go through the steps of reasoning in the light of advancing technology. In the natural state, humans are free and generally respectful to each other, but exploitation exists and needs to be accounted for. Without laws, everyone is legislature and judge in one, which leads to unfairness and insecurity about what to expect from each other. This culminates in the people agreeing on a social contract, in which they pass this power to a newly created entity - the state. However, the people would not give that freedom away, without retaining as much as possible, so that the goal of a unified legislature and judiciary is still achieved. For this reason, it would not make sense to give away the right to decide on policy, except for practical considerations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Locke was the Father of the the democracies of England and America, the continental European democracies developed under heavy influence of Rousseau. What he would have said can be found &lt;a href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-ii.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Delegated Voting and Classical Theorists II</title><link href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-ii.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Zombiecalypse</name></author><id>tag:zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog,2013-01-13:2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-ii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This continues the series on 
&lt;a href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-i.html"&gt;delegated voting and classical&amp;nbsp;theories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rousseau&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to Locke, who purposes a indirect government in order to extend it to a sufficiently big area, Rousseau held that this was actually a reason, why states should not extend beyond local communities. He assumed that this would lead to less corrupted human beings, who would easily find a consensus. At first glance, it seems ridiculous to say that the internet and other communication technologies would lead humankind to a more natural and more empathic state, one only needs to look at the average discussion on the Web to at least doubt that. Then again, Rousseau failed to provide a proof for his claim in the first place, so what the&amp;#8221;natural human being&amp;#8221; would do is still very much up to&amp;nbsp;discussion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can however analyse how delegated voting would influence the communication structure that would lead to a political decision. For this, one needs to look at the ways, the public can communicate with their leaders today: the media could pick up the story to bring it to the attention of the politicians, but the incentive to do do requires the story to be interesting and concrete. One could also contact the politician directly, but due to the personal distance, one might decide not to do so, if the issue is not very&amp;nbsp;pressing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This direct way of communication would be influenced by the voting system, because one would typically choose delegates that one trusts. It is of course easier to extend trust to people one reckons to know, so many delegates will be from the personal environment of the voter. This at least comes closer than a national state with a parliament to Rousseau&amp;#8217;s ideal&amp;nbsp;order. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the transitivity of the delegation might remove the person, who actually makes the decision, even further from the voter. It might well be the case that the voter has no personal connection to the delegate and might not even have heard of&amp;nbsp;them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In The Social Contract, Rousseau argues that no law is legit unless it is the people, who decided on it. For this, delegate voting offers a more realistic implementation than plainly voting every issue: through delegates, one does not need to invest information cost for voting, if one does not wish&amp;nbsp;to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion I would say that, while not as clearly as Locke, Rousseau would be in favour of a delegated voting&amp;nbsp;system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://zombiecalypse.github.com/Blog/2013/Jan/delegated-voting-and-classical-theorists-iii.html"&gt;next part&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Tocqueville&lt;/strong&gt; will get his say - who argued that there is a
something as too much democracy and surely wouldn&amp;#8217;t be a huge fan of delegated&amp;nbsp;voting.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>